I'm not sure what made me pick it.
我也不知道当时怎么选了
It might have been the price factor.
就是可能考虑价格因素吧
But the prices weren't really that low.
但是价格因素呢也没有很便宜啊
So tomorrow I might switch to a hotel in Yangpu District.
所以明天我可能换到杨浦区的一个酒店啊
It's closer to Bilibili.
就离哔哩哔哩近一点
This time, every time I come to Shanghai, I stay in a different place.
这次啊我每次来上海住的地方都不一样
The first time I stayed at Shanghai University.
上海第一次住的是上海大学
The second time, I stayed near Tibet Road.
第二次住的是嗯西藏路那边
The third time, I stayed in Changning District.
第三次住的是这个长宁区
At a hotel in Changning District.
长宁区那边的一个酒店
But each time, the purpose of my stay is different.
但是呢额每次来讲住的这个目的是不一样的
The purposes are different.
目的是不一样的
So, the places I stay at are also different.
所以来讲呢住的地方也不一样
Now, I feel like I've come here so many times.
然后我感觉就是我现在来这么多次
What district in Shanghai, what location?
上海上海什么区什么位置
I still can't quite remember.
我还是记不太清楚
So this time, I suddenly rushed from Hongqiao to Pudong in the middle of the night.
所以这次突然大半夜从虹桥赶到浦东啊
What topic do I want to discuss with everyone in this episode?
这期我想跟大家讲一个什么样的话题呢
It's about Trump's negotiation strategy.
就是特朗普的这个交易策略啊
As you know, I'm a big fan of the Old Man Trump. I've read all of his books. The Art of the Deal and negotiation. The most crucial point is It's actually about Old Bert's art of negotiation. His negotiation skills are actually quite simple.
大家也知道我比较喜欢老特啊 他的书我都看过 交易的艺术谈判 其中最重要的一点 其实就是老伯特的这个谈判的艺术 他的谈判技巧呢其实就很简单
Anyone who has studied his autobiography,
其实任何研究过他自传的人呢
can know his negotiation techniques.
都能知道他的谈判技巧
It's the so-called Chinese strategy of compromise.
就是所谓的啊中国人的折中策略
What is the Chinese strategy of compromise?
什么叫中国人的折中策略呢
I remember it was Mr. Lu Xun or someone who said,
就是说我记得是鲁迅先生还是谁说过
about the Chinese,
说中国人啊
if you were asked to open a window in a room
如果说啊让你说在屋子里开一扇窗
Most people would try to stop you
大部分人都会阻止你
But if you say
但是如果你如果说啊
I want to tear off the roof of this house
我要把这屋子的房顶掀掉
Most people would try to prevent you
大部分人阻止你
Then you say, well, can I settle for opening a window instead?
然后你说那我退而求其次开扇窗啊
Is that possible?
可不可以
This is a tactic known as extreme pressure
他就是这种叫做极限施压的策略
Because someone makes a very large and unreasonable request
因为别人提了一个很大很过分的要求啊
And finds that the other party disagrees
发现别人不同意
Then, you can settle for less
然后再退而求其次
and others are more likely to agree
别人反而就同意了
Actually, this is the opposite of the foot-in-the-door effect
其实这跟登门槛效应是反过来的
It's about starting big and then going medium or small
这是先大再中或者先大再小啊
The foot-in-the-door effect is about starting small and then going big
登门槛效应的话是以小见大
I'll touch you first
我先摸你
You didn't react
你没反应啊
I'll kiss your hair
吻你头发
You didn’t react. Then you can be more vocal. Then you can get handsy. This is the foot-in-the-door effect. Then they gradually test your boundaries. This is about testing others.
你没反应 亲你没反应 那就可以大声气射啊 那个就可以上下其手 这人就是这样登门槛斧效应 然后一点一点去试探你啊 这是试探别人
If we’re talking about negotiation tactics,
如果是谈判策略的来讲
it’s about exaggerating first,
就是要先要夸大
starting with a price that the other party will definitely reject.
先要说一个对方绝对接受不了的价格
And then pay it off bit by bit.
然后再一点点还
This is actually a strategy we often see.
这其实是一种经常我们见的策略
But in the lab, there's no one like Trump who talks like that.
但是实验室中呢没有像特朗普这样来讲的话
So unreasonable.
这么无理取闹
Or the things he does are quite out of line.
或者说呢他做的一些事情都是比较出格的
It's precisely because they're out of line.
正是因为出格
That he became famous.
所以才出名
Just like Lei Jun's sales strategy.
所以就好像雷军的这个销售策略一样
Didn't Apple say they won't be including chargers anymore?
不是苹果说以后不准备充电器了吗
We also announce that we won't be preparing chargers.
啊我们也宣布不准备充电器
Then we got really slammed for it.
然后呢就被骂被骂的非常狠啊
How could Xiaomi do this?
小米怎么能这样呢
But when it was actually released,
后来实际一发布时候
You'll notice the version that doesn't come with a charger
你会发现那个不准备充电器的版本
It's only one dollar cheaper than the version that comes with a charger.
只比这个准备充电器的版本便宜一块钱啊
That means you can get Xiaomi's power-up for just one yuan.
也就是说你花一块钱就能买到小米的充电器了
It's almost like you didn't spend any money at all.
那等于跟没花钱一样
It's as if it's still being given away for free.
等于还是在送
So this approach successfully marketed the brand.
所以用这种方式成功地营销了一波
There's also the point that he spent 2 million to change the logo, which essentially looked the same as before. Then everyone mocked him for being foolish, but in reality, this move was all about generating traffic and buzz. So in many cases, including when I sued the Xicheng Dama, and in many other situations, the actual intention is not what it seems on the surface.
还有一点他就是说花200万改个logo 其实跟没改一样 然后大家都嘲笑他傻 但其实这一波挣的是流量钱 所以很多的时候包括我起诉西城大妈 包括很多事情来讲 实际醉翁之意不在酒
It's just a facade.
就是表面上啊
Trump is planning to attack Canada
特朗普要进攻加拿大
He's aiming to invade Panama, right?
要进攻巴拿马对吧
Actually, his target is Greenland
那其实啊要进攻格陵兰
He started by marking three locations
他上来就先标注了三个地方
These people would then have to make concessions to prevent the attacks
那么这些人就要对他的不进攻做出让步
That's how it goes
都是这样
So this is a form of blackmail
所以他这是一种讹诈
Distortion can also be seen as a form of extortion
那distortion可以说是一种讹诈勒索
But to put it another way
但是来讲的话
While states may have international law between them,
国家与国家之间的松山虽然说有国际法
in reality, it has no enforcement power.
但是实际上呢他没有发
It is essentially just a diplomatic tool of power and influence.
他实际上只是一个权力实力的外交
So, if you are already the dominant force in a region,
所以你如果已经作为一个地区老大的话呢
you are in a position of authority,
你呢人在其位啊
once you have the power in your hands,
一朝权在手
you can issue orders and make decisions.
便把令来行
If you don’t take action,
如果你不去搞事情的话
then you’ve wasted the power you’ve been given.
那就白拿到这个权利了
So he has to apply maximum pressure
所以他呢一定要极限施压
play this thing like a hand of cards
把这东西呢打一手牌
and then sort out the sequencing
然后呢自己再理清这个测序啊
it's like playing mahjong if your tiles aren't good you stay in the game or you can push the mahjong tiles away it's the same with playing Dou Dizhu you just don't bid If none of the three call it, they draw cards again. Whenever it’s not in their favor, they draw cards again.
你就是让你打麻将一样 你的牌不好啊 你就留局 你就把这个马麻将牌推了啊 打这个这个这个斗地主也是啊 你就不叫啊 三个人都不叫这个就重新抽牌啊 只要不利于自己就就重新抽牌
So I think his ultimate goal might not be to attack Panama.
所以我觉得他最终的目的可能不是进攻巴拿马
It’s not about the attack itself, right?
也不是进攻目的对吧
Attacking Canada, for instance.
进攻这个加拿大
Because everyone knows that if a war is to break out,
因为知道知道大家啊知道进行战争的话呢
preparations for war must be made first.
必须要先进行战争准备
And these preparations require a lot of resources and manpower.
而进行战争准备要到了
A lot of resources and manpower must be mobilized and prepared.
调动大量的资源和人力和进行准备
Otherwise, you see,
否则来讲的话
especially in modern warfare,
因为你作战特别是现代战争
the main things to allocate are resources and all sorts of plans,
需要调配的主要是资源以及各种各样的计划
which need to be meticulously organized.
要做的非常周密才行啊
If you've read Carl von Clausewitz's On War,
如果你读过冯克劳德维茨的战争论
you'll know that even from the wars of Napoleon's era in the 18th century,
你就知道从18世纪的拿破仑时代的战争来讲
things were already quite complex,
开始就已经非常的复杂化了
logistics,
后勤啊
military logistics.
军事后勤学
When it comes to military finance and economics
军事财经学这些东西来讲
why are they mentioned alongside campaign studies and command studies?
为什么被提到这个战役学指挥学呢
When viewed from the same perspective,
同样的高度来讲
it's because modern warfare is becoming increasingly complex.
就是因为它现代战争是越来越复杂了啊
For example, when we talk about deploying artillery,
比如说我们说调动炮兵
you have to consider the weight of the artillery itself,
你就必须要外讲炮兵的自重
the ammunition supply for the artillery,
炮兵的弹药补给
all the preparatory work required for the artillery operations, if you want to use such weapons You need to provide the necessary conditions for this weapon. So, how do we coordinate the supply of nutrients? Such as fuel and all kinds of supplies.
所有炮兵的这些准备的这些工作 你想用这种兵器 你就要为这种兵器提供条件 那么该如何协同补给养料啊 油料各种各样的东西呢
When talking about World War II,
讲二战的时候来讲的话
Aircraft and tanks required fuel.
飞机坦克就需要油啊
In many cases,
很多的时候来讲
We can look at the ongoing conflict between Russia and Ukraine this year.
我们看今年的俄乌冲突之类的啊
But this has been going on for several years.
但是这已经好几年了
Frequently due to tanks running out of fuel.
经常因为坦克没有油料啊
There was no resupply of ammunition.
没有补给弹药的补给
So, problems arose.
所以出现了问题
That's why the logistics capability in modern warfare is crucial.
所以现代战争中调配的能力
And the organization of such logistics.
还有组织啊这些东西
After being attacked, then what?
然后被攻击了以后
There's a need for the ability to replenish.
需要再补充的这种能力
As the saying goes, 'Xiao He manages the logistics behind the scenes'.
所谓的运筹帷幄有萧何
Xiao He's role is absolutely vital.
萧何的作用是非常大的
Deciding which areas need reinforcements
给哪个地方补充兵源
Which location needs additional weapons
给哪个地方补充兵器
Where should we take action
给哪个地方在什么地方采取啊
Replenish supplies
补充给养
And in reality
而且这些东西在现实当中啊
There are time lags
他都是有时间差的
You respond here
你这边做出了反应
But they might not react in time, and new situations could arise
那边可能还来不及反应又会有新的情况
So your intelligence network must communicate very smoothly
所以你的情报网也必须沟通的非常的顺畅
That's why, when it comes to Trump's strategies
所以这就是为什么特朗普的这些东西来讲的话
Actually, it's a bit unreliable
其实呢有点不靠谱
But for most people
但是更多的人来讲
To guard against such unreliability
为了防范这种不靠谱呢
More preparation is needed In this case He only needs to send out a tweet Others have to make three or four steps of preparation This way, he gains the upper hand And after a series of such moves
要进行啊更多的准备 这样来讲的话 他做了一步只需要发个推特啊 别人需要做出三四步的准备 这样他就占据了先机 而且他通过一系列这种操作以后
He can influence the stock market
他可以对股票市场啊
and have a new impact on financial markets across the country and the world
对全国的全世界的金融市场产生新的作用
and when he speaks in this way
而且他这么来说呢来讲的话
it inadvertently makes these arms manufacturers
无意之间呢也让这些军火的
these large military-industrial complexes, quite pleased and happy
这些大型的这些军火复合体呢也高兴也开心
So in many cases
所以很多的时候来讲
how does he motivate people
他如何调动人的这个积极性呢
think about it, if a war really starts
你想如果真的开始打仗了
right?
对不对
Those from Lanzhou, especially those in Washington State,
那些兰州的特别是华盛顿州的人
would they have to flee to places that are not border areas?
是不是就得往不是边境的地方跑呢
So in many cases,
所以很多的时候来讲
many things in reality are in its favor.
现实当中很多东西是有利于它的
This wildfire in California,
加州这次大火
if he were to prepare for a full-scale conflict with Canada,
如果他要是准备跟这个加拿大
then to be honest, the northeastern parts of the U.S., those Lanzhou areas,
真的全面开战的话
including the northwestern parts of those Lanzhou areas,
那其实说实在的东北部的美国那些兰州
The central part, in fact, is the non-rainy belt of the United States.
中部其实来讲美国的不降雨带啊
Many areas in the central region,
这些地方中部的很多地方来讲
can be said to suffer less,
其实可以说不会那么受罪
Tennessee, for instance, doesn't suffer as much, right?
田纳西没有那么受罪对吧
But Washington and the northeastern states, that's not necessarily the case. So a lot of things are such that when you do one thing, it can trigger several reactions from the other side, just like playing Go. Just like when you play Go
但是华盛顿啊跟东北部的这些兰州 那就不一定了 所以很多东西都是他做一件事情 就能引起对方几个反应 就像你玩围棋 就像你玩五子棋一样
Just like when you play chess
就像你下象棋一样
If you can move one piece
如果你能动一个子
It can cause several of the opponent's pieces to react accordingly
就能让对方的好几个子产生相应的这个反应
To put it this way
来讲的话
This is the ultimate strategy
这就是一个最高的高招
So in many cases, I think
所以来讲我觉得很多的时候来讲
When it comes to biographies of celebrities
名人的传记呢
I generally don't like to read them
我一般是不愿意读的
Because celebrity biographies are often filled with narcissistic tendencies and personal interpretations.
因为名人传记充满了自恋情结跟自我的解释
But the books about Trump
但是特朗普的啊这些书
Especially 'The Art of the Deal' which was written in the 1970s and 1980s
特别是交易的艺术成型于七八十年代
His books, before he became president
所以他那些书来讲
He had already written them
在他成为总统之前
So a lot of things
他就已经啊写了
You can see that Trump really has some remarkable qualities
所以很多东西来讲
He gets a lot of attention
你可以看到特朗普这人确实有过人之处啊
A lot of attention
很多关注
In areas he doesn't understand
当然他有他不靠谱的地方
He is definitely unreliable
对他不理不理解的领域
But in areas where he excels
他肯定是不靠谱
Especially in distortion
但是对于一些他比较善于的这种领域来讲的话
And extortion techniques
特别是这种distortion啊
These skills are indeed worth mastering
勒索的技巧
Many times
这个东西确实啊值得被大家掌握
The more closed off you are
很多的时候来讲
The more you will be valued
越封闭啊
So I highly recommend that everyone Read Trump's autobiographies as soon as possible
你就会越受重视 所以这个东西大家能够利用到现实当中 我特别建议大家 赶紧把特朗普的几本自传都看了